Finding Aid for a Collection of Ethiopic Manuscripts LSC.0937
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Title (Romanized): Mazemura Dawit, Asmat Uniform title: Magical Prayers Title (English): Psalms (for magical purposes)., 20th.; Manuscript number: 21; Vellum, folded like concertina, text on both sides. Size: 60 mm x 65 mm x 5 mm No binding, composed of two strips of vellum. The text is in black i
  Three chapters from Psalms with magical prayer instruction.
- Title (Romanized): ?alot b?eneta ?amasno ma?esaru lasayetan Uniform title: Magical Prayers Title (English): Prayer to Destroy the Binding of Satan., 20th.; Manuscript number: 22; Vellum, folded like concertina, text on both sides. Size: 55 mm x 53 mm x 14 mm No binding, composed of two strips of vellum. The text is in black ink, but like other magical books, the beginning of each prayer and some magical names ('asmat') are in red ink. The magical images are drawn with black and red inks. Twenty nine magical illustrations in black and red ink. (Box 4)
  This magical book is written for the healing of the disease called Barya (epilepsy).
  The owner was Amata Egeziabeher (a woman), mentioned near the middle of the text.
  Magical prayer against demons, zar, epilepsy, and so on. In addition to the magical or hidden names, it also contains certain passages from the the gospels.
- Title (Romanized): Sayefa Malakot Uniform title: Prayers Title (English): Sword of Divinity., 1900s.; Manuscript number: 23; Layout: One column per page, 10 lines of text per page Vellum, 56 pages Size: 86 mm x 70 mm x 14 mm Binding: hard paper boards, but text in vellum No illustrations. (Box 4)
  The owner might be Waleda Hana, who is mentioned on p. 9.
  Magical prayer with magical names (hidden names) for seven days.
- Title (Romanized): Mazemura Dawit; salota nabiyat; Weddasé Maryam; Aneqa?a Berhan Uniform title: Psalter Title (English): Psalter, Old and New Testament Canticles, Praise of Mary, and The Gate of Light., 18th c.; Manuscript number: 24; Vellum, 360 pages; Layout: One column per page, 21 lines of text per page Vellum, 360 pages Size: 160 mm x 120 mm x 64 mm Text in black ink. Beginning of each chapter, title of the chapter, and names of God, Mary, and the angels in red ink. Binding: stamped leather over wooden board. In Psalms, strings of words were missing, but were then inserted above the line or after the line by the same scribe. These additional words (often ten or twelve in a row) are written in the same hand, but smaller The manuscripts composed in eighteen quieres (Box 5)
  On p.1, there is writing and a very crude pencil drawing which says "this is the seal (of) Dejazmach Emru." On p.3, someone tried to erase the writing that said "this psalter is for Dejazmach Emru."
- Title (Romanized): Masehafa Qeddasé Uniform title: Qedasé Title (English): The Book of Missal., 20th c.; Manuscript number: 25; Vellum, 268 pages Layout: Two columns per page, 14 lines of text per page Size: 250mm x 222mm x 60mm Binding: stamped leather over the board Text in black ink. Beginning of each prayer and anaphora, instructions for the priests and deacons, and also the order of pointing and benediction over the Host (bread) and the cup (wine) are in red ink. The manuscript composed in fifteen quires (Box 5)
  The manuscript contains only the fourteen anaphoras which are commonly used in the church. In addition to that, like most published missals, it also contains the Office Prayer, Liton, intercessory prayers, and "enthronement" prayers. The order of the fourteen anaphoras and the following prayers are the same as in the published book of missal.
  The original owner's name is Gabra Selasse (p. 56)
- Title (Romanized): Ta'amra Eyesus Uniform title: Miracles of Jesus Title (English): Miracles of Jesus., 19th c.; Manuscript number: 26; Vellum, 124 pages. Two columns, the majority of the text is in 21 and 25 lines of text per page. Size: 234 mm x 188 mm x 54 mm Text is in black ink. The beginning of each miracle and the names of Jesus and Mary are in red ink. Binding: with wooden board and string. The manuscript is composed of seven quires of eight leaves each and one quire of six leaves. No illustrations. (Box 6)
  The owner is mentioned by the name of Qale Kerestos and Eheta Giyorgis (p. 2, 121). Walata Rufael (probably the second owner) also inserted her name (p. 124). The most recent owner is Abba Gabera Mika'el, who is listed on the end page and put the anathema on those who would try to steal the book.
  Different miracles performed by Jesus. Some of them are similar to stories about his infancy from the apocryphal gospels.
- Title (Romanized): Teregwame Wanegel Uniform title: Commentary Title (English): Commentary on the Gospel., 19th.; Manuscript number: 27; Layout: Two columns; lines of text per page vary Vellum and paper, 214 pages Size: 230mm x 168mm x 58mm Binding: wooden board Text in black ink, the beginnig of each section (guba'e) is in red. The manuscript is composed of one quire of eight leaves, five quiries of ten leaves each, and two quires of fourteen leaves each, one quire additional of six leaves. (Box 6)
  Hayele Mariam is the owner (p. ??)
  Commentary on the Gospel of Mathew and Mark. Most of the text is in abbreviated form. The purpose of the manuscript is to serve as a pneumatic or reference book for the 'andem' student trying to memorize the whole text of the gospels.
- Title (Romanized): Mazemura Dawit,?alota nabiyat, Mahalya Mahaley,Weddasé Maryam, Anqasa Berhan Uniform title: Psalter Title (English): Psalter, Old and New Testament canticles, Song of Songs, Praise of Mary, and The Gate of Light., Late 19th c.; Manuscript number: 28; Layout: Psalms and the canticles are written in one column per page and 22 lines of text per page. Praise of Mary and Gate of Light are written in two columns. Vellum, 382 pages Size: 154 mm x 93 mm x 52 mm Binding: wooden boards The majority of the manuscript is composed of seven quires of twelve leaves each. Text is in black ink. The opening verse of the chapters of the Psalter, the first word of the prayers from Praise of Mary and Gate of Light, and the name of the Virgin Mary are in red ink. Illustrations p. 2, 3 (Box 6)
- Title (Romanized): Dersana Mahyawi, ?alota Kidan Uniform title: Homily and Office Prayer Title (English): Homily of the Savior and Office Prayer., 19th c.; Manuscript number: 29; Layout: two columns, the majority of the manuscript is eighteen lines of text per page Vellum, 210 pages Size: 212 mm x 169 mm x 50 mm Binding: Wooden board covered with sewn khaki fabric and khaki handle Most of the manuscript is composed of quires of eight leaves each. Text in black ink but the opening of prayers and the name of Christ is in red ink. No illustrations. (Box 6)
  The first owner is Waleda Takela Hayemanot; but the second owner, Gabera Mika'el, cancelled the previous owner's name and inserted his own name and his wife's name Amata Mika'el (pp. 265).
- Title (Romanized): Arede'et Uniform title: Prayer book Title (English): The Book of the Disciples., 1900s.; Manuscript number: 30; Vellum, 88 pages. One column of text per page, 17 lines of text per page. Size: 132 mm x 89 mm x 32 mm Binding is wooden boards and string. Text is in black ink, the beginning of each prayer and Christ's name are in red ink. The manuscript is composed of four quires of ten leaves each and one quire of four leaves. No illustrations. (Box 7)
  The Book of the Disciples is the Christian version of a book also used by the Beta Israel (Falasha or Ethiopian Jewish) community. It narrates how Jesus told his disciples his hidden names.
- Title (Romanized): A'emada Mesetir, Ra'eya Barok Uniform title: Dogma (doctrine) of the church, Catechism of the Ethiopian Church Title (English): The Pillars of Mystery, The Vision of Baruch., 1900s.; Manuscript number: 31; Layout: pp.1-22 one column per page, pp. 23-138 two columns,14 lines of text per page Vellum, 138 pages Binding: wooden board Size: 194 mm x 123mm x 45mm Text in black ink. Beginning of each chapter, divine names, and church fathers names in red ink. Manuscript is composed of seven quires of ten leaves each. (Box 7)
  The Pillars of Mystery is a very important doctrinal book in the Ethiopian Orthodox Church. It is the summery of the faith of the Orthodox church and the basis of the systematic theology of the church. Based on the Nicene Creed it presents the faith of the Orthodox fathers. The manuscript is the early Amharic translation of the Ge'ez text. The Vision of Baruch is one of five books attributed to Baruch, the scribe of the Prophet Jeremiah. The Vision of Baruch is also called The Fifth Baruch or The Ethiopic Apocalypse of Baruch, also used by the Ethiopian Jewish (Beta Israel) community. For a detailed discussion about the Beta Israel/Falasha version, see Leslau's Falasha Antology (1951).
  Bedlu Wolde Mika'el's seven generations are listed (p.118).
  The Pillars of Mystery is the discussion of the teaching of the the mystery of the trinity, the incarnation, baptism, holy communion, and the resurrection of the dead. It is in the format of questions and answers from the Old and New Testaments and also from the patristic writings. The second book, The Vision of Baruch, is the Christian rather than Jewish version of the Ethiopic Apocalypse of Baruch. When the Angel Sutu'el took Baruch to Heaven, he saw the punishment of sinners and the reward of the just.
- Title (Romanized): Qeddasé Maryam, Kidan, Malke'a Madehané Alam, Malek'a Mika?él, Malek'a Edom Uniform title:Anaphora, Images of the Saints Title (English): Anaphora of St. Mary, Office Prayer, Image of the Savior of the World, Image of St. Michael, Image of Edom., 1900s?.; Manuscript number: 32; Layout: One column of text per page, 14 lines of text per page Vellum, 178 pages Size: 116 mm x 83 mm x 42 mm Binding: Wooden boards Text in black ink. Angels' and saints' names and the beginning of prayers are in red ink. Some border designs; no other illustrations. Quires? (Box 7)
  In the Fasting of the Assumption especially, it is common to read the Anaphora of St. Mary. Listening to the commentaries on this Anaphora of St. Mary and also the Praise of Mary are at the center of the mass and private devotion.
- Title (Romanized): Tamahesanku … Giyorgis Uniform title: Prayer book Title (English): I Beseech George (Supplication to St. George)., 1900s.; Manuscript number: 33; Layout: two columns per page, with 13 lines of text per page. Vellum, 92 pages Size: 147 mm x 105 mm x 7 mm Binding: Without cover, but string binding The manuscript is composed of four quires of ten leaves and one quire of six leaves. Text is in black ink with the names of saints in red ink. Several notes in the upper margin of the pages serve as captions for the illustrations of the martyrdom of St. George, but some of the explanations and the images don't match. Probably the captions were written first and the illustrations done later. Twenty-three illustrations of scenes from the saint's life. Most in black ink, some in pencil. descriptive data: Text in black ink, the name of the saint in red ink. The manuscript is composed of quires of Ten leaves each (Box 7)
  Based on the hagiography of St. George, the author mentions the passion of the saint and asks for the protection of the martyr. Following each prayer, there is a list of hidden names which have magical power.
  The manuscript contains prayers or supplications to St. George.
- Title (Romanized): ?elota Kidan; Temehereta Hebu'at,;Malk'a Maryam; Malk'a Iyesus; Malk'a Giyorgis; Sayefa Sellasé;QedaseMareyam; Malek'a Sellasé;Malk'a Takela Hayemanot; Malk'a Medehane Alem. Uniform title: Images of the Saints Title (English): Office Prayer, Mystagogia, Binding of Demons, Image of Mary, Image of Jesus, Image of George, Sword of Trinity, Anaphora of St. Mary, Image of Trinity, Image of St. Takela Haymanot, Image of Medehane Alem., 1874-1926.; Manuscript number: 34; Layout: two columns of text, 15 lines of text per page. Vellum and paper, 432 pages Size: 155 mm x 115 mm x 59 mm Binding is wooden boards with stamped red leather. In leather case with strap (very typical case). The manuscript is composed of nine quires of ten leaves each, seven quires of twelve leaves each. The remaining four quires have five, six, nine, eleven,and fourteen leaves each. The text is in black ink; the names of God, angels, and saints, including the scribes and the owners, and the first line of each book, are in red ink. Pp. 323-432 in paper leaves, the rest of the manuscript in vellum No portraits but geographic drawings as borders. (Box 7)
  The owner of the manuscript is Gabera Walede and his wife Askala Mareyam (pp. 269). The second owner is Walda Meskel (pp. 141).
  The manuscript includes the Office Prayer and Mystagogia prayers which, according to church tradition, the apostles received from Jesus Christ after his resurrection. It also includes 'malek' or images of Jesus and the saints.
- Title (Romanized): Arganon Uniform title: Hymns for St. Mary Title (English): Arganon (Praise) of Mary., 16th c.-17th c.; Manuscript number: 35; Layout: Two columns per page, 18 lines of text per page Vellum, 256 pages Size: 222mm x 190mm x 80mm Binding is wooden boards Texts in black ink, the beginning of each prayer and St. Mary's name is in red ink. The manuscript is composed of quires of eight and ten leaves each. Illustrations????? (Box 8)
  The manuscript contains one of the writingd of Abba Giyorgis of Gascha or Segla in Ethiopia. Following the advent of the Book of the Miracles of St. Mary, Abba Giyorgis was vigorously promoting the cult of St. Mary. In Arganon he intertwined biblical and patristic writings of the church with his new Mariology.
- Title (Romanized): Wanegel Zayohanes Uniform title: New Testament (Gospel) Title (English): Gospel of John., 19th c.; Manuscript number: 36; Vellum, 208 pages; Layout: Two columns of text, 17 lines of text per page. Vellum, 208 pages Size: 142 mm x 100 mm x 47 mm Binding: wooden boards with a leather cover Text in black ink, some names and titles of the chapters are in red. No illustrations. Quires? (Box 8)
  The fourth gospel is the most copied book in Ethiopic manuscript collections. Apart from its prominent place in the church, the Gospel of John is the starting point in traditional church school for reading church books and developing Ge'ez vocabulary.
  The owner of the manuscript is a woman by the name of Walata Berehan (Daughter of light) (p. 204)
- Title (Romanized): Dersana Raguel, Malek'a Raguel,Malek'a Giyorgis Uniform title: Homily on St Raguel, Image of Saints Title (English): Homily on St Raguel, Image of Raguel, Image of George., 19th.; Manuscript number: 37; Layout: one column of text per page, 11 lines of text per page. Vellum, 94 pages Size: 118mm x 88mm x 19mm Binding: wooden boards with stamped leather cover Text in black ink. The beginning of the text and the saint's name is in red ink. The manuscript composed in six quires of one quire of 2 leaves two quires of 8 leaves and three qiures of 10 leaves. (Box 8)
- Title (Romanized): Malek'a Maryam, Malek'a Eyasus Uniform title: Image of Mary, Image of Jesus Title (English): Image of Mary, Image of Jesus., 20th.; Manuscript number: 38; Layout: one column of text per page, 13 lines of text per page Vellum, 76 pages Size: 115 mm x 85 mm x 32 mm The manuscript is composed of quires of six and eight leaves each. Binding: wooden boards with string. The back board is broken. Texts in black ink, the beginning of each prayer and Christ's name are in red ink. Some border designs, but no other illustrations. (Box 8)
- Title (Romanized): Sa'atat Uniform title: Horologium Title (English): The Hours., 19th.; Manuscript number: 39; Layout: one column per page, mostly 13 lines of text per page, but it varies. Vellum. 160 pages Size: 110 mm x 85 mm x 40 mm Binding: wooden boards Text in black ink, some names and beginning of each prayer in red ink. The manuscript is composed of ten quires of 8 leaves each. No illustrations. (Box 8)
  The latter owner is listed as "Priest Mogas" (p. 152).
- Title (Romanized): Wanegel Zayohans Uniform title: Gospel of John Title (English): Gospel of John., 19th.; Manuscript number: 40; Layout: two columns per page, 17 lines of text per page Vellum, 150 pages Size: 150 mm x 110 mm x 43 mm Binding is wooden boards with stamped leather The manuscript is composed of five quires of ten leaves each, two quires of eight leaves each, and one quire of nine leaves. Text is in black ink; the beginning of the section (me'eraf) and the name of Jesus are in red ink. Illustrations on pp. 2 and 149, and decorated borders elsewhere. (Box 9)
  Part of the canon of Ethiopian Orthodox Tewahedo Church, the Gospel of John is the most popular gospel. It is part of the curriculum in the early stages of traditional church education.
  The name of the owner has been deleted. The second owner is listed as Kidana Mareyam (p. 146). Also, with a crude hand are added the words, "This book is for Ato Gabera Mikael" (p. 149).
  The Ethiopic version of the Gospel of John has special characteristics concerning the method of dividing chapters. Ethiopian scholars divided the gospel into more chapters to help students to memorize the gospel with its commentary.
- Title (Romanized): Tasea'elotata Zenahomu la'abew Manakosat Gebesaweyan Uniform title: Monastic book Title (English): Philoxenus or Questions on the Sayings of the Egyptian Fathers., 1700s or 1800s.; Manuscript number: 41; Vellum, 216 pages Two columns per page, 20 lines of text per page. Size: 190mm x 170mm x 56mm The manuscript is composed 12 quires of one quire of 2 leaves one quire of eight leaves ten quires of ten leaves Text in black ink. The beginning of each chapter (each part) and also the names of saints and church fathers in red ink. Binding: wooden board (broken) (Box 9)
  According to the tradition of the church, and as it says in the introductory part of the text, this book was written by Philoxenus, Bishop of Mabbug or Hierapolis (modern Aleppo of Syria), one of the defenders of the non-Chalcedonian (Jacobite) movement. It is based on the collection of The Sayings of the Desert Fathers. Some modern historians reject the idea that Philoxenus authored this book and attribute it to Dadiso Qatrayas, a Nestorian monk of today's Qatar. For more on this debate, see the "Filkeseyus" entry in Encyclopedia Aethiopica, vol. ? (Hamburg, 19??).
  The name of the previous owner is erased and written over with the name Aseqa Mika'el (P. 5 and 212).
  The formal text is accompanied by extensive notes in the margin in Amharic, called 'anedemta' commentary, which serves as a reminder to the reader of commentaries about the specific words or passages next to which the notes are written.
- Title (Romanized): Ma?ehafa Qeddasé Uniform title: Qedasé Title (English): Book of Missal., 1874-1913.; Manuscript number: 42; Vellum, 184 pages; Layout: Two columns per page, text lines per page varies. Vellum, 184 pages Size: 246 mm x 185 mm x 79 mm Binding is wooden boards and string Text in black ink. Beginning of each prayer and anaphora with instructions for Deacon and Priest in red ink. Includes musical notation. No illustrations. Quires???? (Box 9)
  The manuscript contains office prayer, Liton, supplications, and seven anaphoras. The anaphoras included in this manuscript are used frequently in liturgical services.
- Title (Romanized): Malek'a Giyorgis, Malek'a Mika?él, Uniform title: Malek'e Title (English): Image of George, Image of Michael., 19th.; Manuscript number: 43; Layout: one column per page, average thirteen lines of text per page. Vellum, 68 pages. Size: 120 mm x 90 mm x 18 mm Text is in black ink. The beginning of each prayer and the name of the saints are in red ink. The manuscript is composed in four quires of eight leaves each. (Box 9)
  These two 'maleke' are the most popular prayers among the priests and some educated churchmen, especially Dabeteras. The manuscript has very interesting miniatures of various saints and demons. These drawings are used for magical purposes.
  On p. 4, the owner wrote in crude handwriting "By the authority of Peter and Paul, be cursed. This book belongs to Aleqa Bezabeh Kassa." But on p. 34 the owner is mentioned as Gebra Mareyam.
- Title (Romanized): Qeddasé Maryam Uniform title: Qedasé Title (English): Anaphora of St. Mary., 20th c.; Manuscript number: 44; Layout: One column per page, eleven lines of text per page. Vellum, 84 pages Binding is wooden board. Size: 112 mm x 80 mm x 30 mm The manuscript is composed of four quires of eight leaves each and two quires of four leaves each. Text is in black ink. The instruction for priests and deacons and the name of St. Mary are in red ink. Decorative borders but no other illustrations. (Box 9)
  The small size of the manuscript indicates that it was used for private prayer.In the Fasting of the Assumption especially, it is common to read the Anaphora of St. Mary. Listening to the commentaries on this anaphora and Praise of Mary are at the center of the liturgy and private devotion.
- Title (Romanized): Ta'amra Maryam Uniform title: Miracles of St. Mary, Miracles of Jesus, Bible Title (English): Miracles of St. Mary, Miracles of Jesus, Readings from the Bible., 1889-1913.; Manuscript number: 45; Vellum, 176 pages Two columns per page, lines of text per page vary. Wooden boards without leather; with string binding. In leather case with strap. Size: 278 mm x 220 mm x 55 mm The manuscript is composed of ten quires of ten leaves each. Text in black ink. The beginning of each miracle and the name of St. Mary are in red ink. Decorative border illustrations. (Box 10)
- Title (Romanized): ?alot ba?eneta bareya; ?alota Mastem Uniform title: Magical prayers Title (English): Prayers against Epilepsy, Prayers of Mastem., 19th.; Manuscript number: 46; Vellum, scroll One column Size: 2245 mm x 110 mm Text in black ink. Some words and divine and owner's names in red ink. Illustrations: two images in ink and color of angels and one magical drawing. (Box 10)
  A magical scroll with magical prayers against epilepsy and also prayers for the binding of demons.
  The scroll was written for Walata Eyasus (her secular name is Berenash).
  A magical prayer for the binding (or drowning) of demons. The prayers for the binding of demons is for seven days, followed by horoscope analysis of the owner and her magical hidden name.
- Title (Romanized): Lefafa ?deq Uniform title: Magical Prayers Title (English): Bandlet of Righteousness., 20th c.; Manuscript number: 47; Layout: One column per page, 9 lines of text per page Vellum, 68 pages Size: 83 mm x 60 mm x 24 mm Binding is wooden boards and the manuscript is in a leather case with a strap so it can be placed around the neck. The manuscript is composed of four quires of eight leaves each. Text is in black ink. The beginning of each prayer and the name of saints are in red ink. No illustrations. (Box 10)
  It is a typical magical book that is popular among Ethiopian Orthodox nuns as a talisman. The nuns and older women put this manuscript around their necks. It also is put on the necks of children and animals when they become sick.
  Amata Mareyam and Walata Kidan are the owners of the manuscript (both of them are women).
  Like the Egyptian Book of the Dead, this book is also filled with the prayers of the soul on the way to heaven.